Guide to the Joseph A. Sinsheimer Papers, 1962-1987 RL.10056
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Joseph A. Sinsheimer papers
1962-1987
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Sinsheimer, Joseph Andrew, 1962-
RL.10056
5 Linear Feet 689 items
Joseph A. Sinsheimer graduated from Duke University in 1987 with an A.B. in History. He recorded oral histories of the Mississippi civil rights movement between 1983 and 1987, with grant support from the Lyndhurst Foundation. Collection includes audio recordings and transcripts of oral history interviews and speeches regarding the Student Nonviolent Coordinating Committee in Mississippi in the 1960s, with brief summaries. Focus is on the "Freedom Summer" of 1964. Notable interviews include Robert Parris Moses, Sam Block, Hazel Palmer, Jesse Jackson, Gray Evans, Frank Smith, and many more. Collection also contains a small amount of manuscript materials from the civil rights era, including clippings, reports, scrapbooks, and correspondence.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Provenance
The Joseph A. Sinsheimer Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 1987.
Historical Note
Joseph A. Sinsheimer graduated from Duke University in 1987 with an A.B. in History. He recorded oral histories of the Mississippi civil rights movement between 1983 and 1987, with grant support from the Lyndhurst Foundation.
Collection Overview
The collection chronicles the work of the Student Nonviolent Coordinating Committee (SNCC) and its involvement with resident civil rights activists in Mississippi. Materials consist primarily of recorded oral histories and their transcriptions, but also extend to speeches and unpublished papers. The records date from 1962 to 1987, and were compiled and collected by Duke University alumnus Joseph A. Sinsheimer with the support of a fellowship from the Lyndhurst Foundation.
Local activists represent their experiences in a series of twenty-five interviews that were conducted at movement centers throughout Mississippi, including McComb, Jackson, Greenwood, and Clarksdale. Leading SNCC activists Samuel Block, David Dennis, and Silas McGhee are also represented in interviews conducted between 1983 and 1987. There are also four extensive interviews and transcribed speeches of noted SNCC activist and leader of the Mississippi civil rights movement Robert Moses, as well as interviews of community leaders C.C. Bryant and Hazel Palmer, conducted by Moses himself. The collection also features unpublished speeches and papers given in the 1960s; additionally, transcripts of exchanges at academic conferences extend the scope of the collection to reconstructions of events by historians in the 1970s and 1980s. The collection also contains court records and correspondence to national leaders like Hubert Humphrey and Robert Kennedy, which report on the use of organized violence in the counter-efforts of segregationists.
Sinsheimer's records have already been cited by historians Taylor Branch and William Chafe, and played a significant role in the 1994 documentary "Freedom on my Mind." Although Sinsheimer's published articles on the Mississippi Movement have focused on the resistance of SNCC to segregationists policies and organized violence, the documentation of this collection sheds light on a wider range of concerns. The interviews detail the role of the black church in organizational activities; sexism within the movement; the establishment of the Mississippi Freedom Democratic Party in 1964; black nationalism and the role of white student workers in the civil rights movement after the "Freedom Summer;" as well as the significance of national media in the struggle.
Civil rights -- Mississippi; Mississippi -- Race relations; Mississippi -- Ethnic relations; Minorities -- Mississippi -- History; Civil rights workers -- Mississippi -- History; Civil rights -- Alabama; Voter registration -- Mississippi; Harris, David, 1946-; Payne, Bruce L.; Evers, Medgar Wiley, 1925-1963; Moses, Robert Parris, 1888-; Lowenstein, Allard K.; Mississippi Freedom Democratic Party; Jenkins, Tim; Zinn, Howard, 1922-2010; Student Nonviolent Coordinating Committee (U.S.); Emmerich, John; Council of Federated Organizations (U.S.)
- Interviews and speeches, 1963-1987; 1; 6 Linear Feet 157 items, 8 single-row cassette boxes, 2 paige boxes
  Scope and Contents
  The oral history interviews in this collection were largely conducted and collected by Joseph Sinsheimer. The materials have been arranged by interview, and also include some speeches and occasional interviews by other historians, such as Howard Zinn, Clayborne Carson, and John Dittmer. Some transcripts do not have accompanying audiocassettes; likewise, some audiocassettes do not include a transcript. Sinsheimer's interviews were often accompanied by a memorandum in which he offered a brief biographical note on the interviewee and detailed the subjects covered in the interview. These notes have been included below when present in the collection.
  - Adams, Victoria Gray interviewed by Joseph Sinsheimer, 1987 August 23
    Scope and Contents note
    Leading civil rights activist in Hattiesburg, MS. Interview with Sinsheimer. Gray discussed: Vernon Dahmer's leadership in the local civil rights campaign; her first encounter with SNCC field secretary Hollis Watkins; economic reprisals directed against black civil rights workers by the local white community; lack of adult leadership in Mississippi movement; Lawrence Guyot's role in the Hattiesburg campaign.
    - Transcript (Box 1)
  - Adams, Victoria Gray interviewed by John Dittmer, 1989 May 8; 12
    Access Restrictions
    Rights to this interview have not been shared with the donor or the Rubenstein Library. Please contact the Rubenstein Library for further information on accessing this resource.
    - Original audiocassette (Box 6, Audio-cassette RL10056-CS-0062)
    - Use copy audiocassette (Box 3, Audio-cassette RL10056-CS-0011)
  - Allen, Emma interviewed by Joseph Sinsheimer, 1986 May 5; 1
    Local civil rights activist in Greenwood, MS. Interview with Sinsheimer. Allen discussed: Robert Moses' leadership role in the movement; the role of different black churches in supporting the Greenwood movement; black Greenwood's economic boycott of Slim Henderson's store in 1964; the difficulty of attempting to register to vote in Greenwood.
    - Original audiocassette, 72 minutes (Box 6, Audio-cassette RL10056-CS-0052)
    - Transcript (Box 1)
    - Use copy audiocassette (Box 3, Audio-cassette RL10056-CS-0001)
  - Block, Sam interviewed by Joseph Sinsheimer, 1986 December 12; 2
    SNCC's lead organizer in Greenwood, MS, 1962-1963. Interview with Sinsheimer. Block discussed: his childhood experiences with racism in Mississippi; his "recruitment" into the civil rights movement by Amzie Moore; developing a voter registration campaign in Greenwood; Cleveland Jordan's role in developing the Greenwood movement; Rev. Aaron Johnson's decision to open the First Christian Church to the movement; working with SNCC field secretary Willie Peacock in Greenwood; developing a voter registration campaign in Itta Bena, Mississippi; Bob Moses' role in the Mississippi campaign; the role of SNCC Executive Secretary James Forman in the Mississippi movement; the difficulty in getting black churches to open their doors to the movement; SNCC's relationship with the NAACP in the state; the psychological effects of the March on Washington in 1963; the need for greater staff education in the Mississippi movement.
    - Original audiocassette, 1 of 3 (Box 6, Audio-cassette RL10056-CS-0053)
    - Original audiocassette, 2 of 3 (Box 6, Audio-cassette RL10056-CS-0054)
    - Original audiocassette, 3 of 3 (Box 6, Audio-cassette RL10056-CS-0055)
    - Transcript (Box 1)
    - Use copy audiocassette, 1 of 3 (Box 3, Audio-cassette RL10056-CS-0002)
    - Use copy audiocassette, 2 of 3 (Box 3, Audio-cassette RL10056-CS-0003)
    - Use copy audiocassette, 3 of 3 (Box 3, Audio-cassette RL10056-CS-0004)
  - Bryant, C.C. with Robert Moses, 1983 July 9
    Branch president of the McComb, MS, NAACP, 1954-1985. Transcript of Bryant and Robert Moses at the Mississippi Voices of the Civil Rights Movement Conference, McComb, MS.
    Conditions Governing Access
    - Transcript (Box 1)
  - Bryant, C.C. interviewed by Joseph Sinsheimer, 1985 February 7; 3
    Branch president of the McComb, MS, NAACP, 1954-1985. Interview with Sinsheimer. Bryant discussed: Amzie Moore's role in sending Robert Moses to McComb; voter registration classes in McComb and Amite County in 1961; the murder of Herbert Lee; working with Robert Moses during the 1961 voter registration campaign; civil rights activity in McComb during the 1964 Freedom Summer project; McComb's reaction to white civil rights workers in 1964; the role of the U.S. Justice Dept. in MS civil rights activity.
    - Original audiocassette (Box 6, Audio-cassette RL10056-CS-0056)
    - Transcript (Box 1)
    - Use copy audiocassette (Box 3, Audio-cassette RL10056-CS-0005)
  - Coles, Robert interviewed by Joseph Sinsheimer, 1983 November 19; 4
    Author of the Children of Crisis series; advisor to SNCC, 1963-1964. Interview with Sinsheimer. Coles discussed: the intense media scrutiny of the Mississippi Freedom Summer Project; the tension between SNCC staff and student volunteers; recollections of Dennis Sweeney; the Mississippi Freedom Democratic Party (MFDP) challenge to the all-white delegation at the 1964 Democratic National Convention in Atlantic City.
    - Original audiocassette (Bob Moses interview starts at 30 minutes on side 2) (Box 6, Audio-cassette RL10056-CS-0057)
    - Transcript (Box 1)
    - Use copy audiocassette (Box 3, Audio-cassette RL10056-CS-0006)
  - Criss, Sarah interviewed by Joseph Sinsheimer, 1986 May 8; 5
    Reporter for the Memphis Commercial-Appeal, 1956-1980. Interview with Sinsheimer. Criss discussed: the pressure on white Southern newspaper reporters; the presence of the Ku Klux Klan in Greenwood; the role of various white officials in Greenwood, including former City Attorney Hardy Lott and former mayor Charles Sampson; reaction to the Beckwith trial (for the murder of Medgar Evers); the membership of the White Legal Defense Fund formed to support Beckwith; Hardy Lott's influence on the Greenwood Citizens Council; Greenwood's reaction to the 1964 Civil Rights Act; the tension between large plantation owners and other civic leaders in Greenwood over the issue of recruiting manufacturing jobs to the town in the late 1940s and 1950s.
    - Original audiocassette (Box 6, Audio-cassette RL10056-CS-0058)
    - Transcript (Box 1)
    - Use copy audiocassette (Box 3, Audio-cassette RL10056-CS-0007)
  - Emmerich, John, 1985 July 16; 7
    - Transcript (Box 1)
  - Dennis, David interviewed by John Dittmer, 1983 July 12; 6
    Head of CORE in Mississippi during the 1960s. Interview with John Dittmer. Dennis discussed: the development of the Council of Federated Organizations (COFO) in Mississippi; the development of the civil rights movement in Jackson, MS; the movements "failure" after 1964; his reaction to the Democratic National Convention in Atlantic City, 1964; the role of the Mississippi Freedom Democratic Party after 1964; the rise of black nationalism in Mississippi; the role of white students in the movement.
    - Transcript (Box 1)
  - Evans, Gray interviewed by Joseph Sinsheimer, 1985 July 10; 8
    Leader of the moderate white community in Greenwood, MS; prosecuting attorney for Greenwood during most of the early 1960s. Interview with Sinsheimer. Evans discussed: his relationship with U.S. Congressman Frank Smith and other federal officials; negotiating on the telephone with Robert Kennedy; his relationship with U.S. Justice Dept. official John Doar; Hardy Lott's influence on Greenwood officials.
    - Original audiocassette (Box 6, Audio-cassette RL10056-CS-0059)
    - Transcript (Box 1)
    - Use copy audiocassette (Box 3, Audio-cassette RL10056-CS-0008)
  - Evans, Gray interviewed by Joseph Sinsheimer, 1986 May 5; 9
    Leader of the moderate white community in Greenwood, MS; prosecuting attorney for Greenwood during most of the early 1960s. Interview with Sinsheimer. Evans discussed: tensions between Greenwood city officials, 1963-1964; a fistfight between Buff Hammond and Charlie Sampson that sprung from integration efforts at the Leflore Theatre; race relations in Greenwood in the late 1950s; leaders of the Greenwood Citizens Council.
    - Original audiocassette (Box 6, Audio-cassette RL10056-CS-0060)
    - Transcript (Box 1)
    - Use copy audiocassette (Box 3, Audio-cassette RL10056-CS-0009)
  - Frank, Barney interviewed by Joseph Sinsheimer, 1983 November 14; 10
    Student volunteer for the Mississippi Freedom Summer Project, 1964; member of the U.S. House of Representatives from Massachusetts, 1981-2013. Interview with Sinsheimer. Frank discussed: how he was recruited to the project by Al Lowenstein; his experiences that summer in Jackson, MS; Al Lowenstein's reaction to the MFDP's Atlantic City challenge.
    - Original audiocassette (Box 6, Audio-cassette RL10056-CS-0061)
    - Transcript (Box 1)
    - Use copy audiocassette (Box 3, Audio-cassette RL10056-CS-0010)
  - Greene Family interviewed by Clayborne Carson, 1978 September 16; 11
    Active in the civil rights movement in Greenwood during the 1960s. Interview with Clayborne Carson.
    - Transcript (Box 1)
  - Group interview (Charles Smith, William Jenkins, Joe Martin, Rev. Harry Bowie, Edith Moore, L.B. Butler, and Jessie Devines) interviewed by Joseph Sinsheimer, 1985 February 16; 13
    Participants include Charles Smith, William Jenkins, Joe Martin, Rev. Harry Bowie, Edith Moore, L.B. Butler, and Jessie Devines, all civil rights activists in McComb, MS. Interview with Sinsheimer. Participants discussed: their childhood in the segregated South; black role models in the segregated South; leadership of C.C. Bryant in McComb race relations; the creation of the Pike County Voter's League in the 1940s; a school walk-out by a group of black Burgland High School students in the fall of 1961; changes in the movement from 1961 to 1964; role of Robert Moses in the Mississippi campaign.
    - Transcript (Box 1)
  - Guyot, Lawrence interviewed by Joseph Sinsheimer, 1987 May 4; 14
    SNCC field secretary from Mississippi. Interview with Sinsheimer. Guyot discussed: Amzie Moore's role in the Delta civil rights movement; development of Greenwood, MS voter registration campaign, 1962-1963; arrest of the Greenwood SNCC staff in 1963 by white authorities; the role of Ed Cothran in the Greenwood campaign; the role of black women in the Mississippi movement; the role of Tougaloo College in the development of civil rights activity in Hattiesburg, MS, 1962-1963; the success of the Freedom School program in Hattiesburg; the credential challenge by the Mississippi Freedom Democratic Party in 1964; SNCC's focus or lack of focus on economic issues in Mississippi in the mid-1960s; the correlation between information and power; the development of the Delta Ministry in Mississippi; how to avoid movement "burnout"; the 1988 presidential election.
    - Original audiocassette, 1 of 2 (Box 6, Audio-cassette RL10056-CS-0063)
    - Original audiocassette, 2 of 2 (June Johnson on side 2) (Box 6, Audio-cassette RL10056-CS-0064)
    - Transcript (Box 1)
    - Use copy audiocassette, 1 of 2 (Box 3, Audio-cassette RL10056-CS-0012)
    - Use copy audiocassette, 2 of 2 (Box 3, Audio-cassette RL10056-CS-0013)
  - Gwin, Arnold "Bo" interviewed by Joseph Sinsheimer, 1986 May 7; 15
    Former legal associate of Hardy Lott. Interview with Sinsheimer. Gwin discussed: the role of the Greenwood Citizens Council in civic affairs; the black community's boycott of Greenwood's white merchants, 1967-1968; Hardy Lott's relationship to U.S. senators Eastland and Stennis; the leadership of the Greenwood Citizens Council; Lott's relationship with U.S. Federal District Judge Clayton; relationship between Judge Clayton and U.S. Justice Dept. representative John Doar; Lott's role as city attorney; Greenwood's white community support of Beckwith after Evers' murder; members of the White Legal Defense Fund set up to support Beckwith.
    - Original audiocassette (Box 6, Audio-cassette RL10056-CS-0065)
    - Transcript (Box 1)
    - Use copy (Box 3, Audio-cassette RL10056-CS-0014)
  - Harding, Vincent - speech, 1964; 16
    Rights to this speech have not been shared with the donor or the Rubenstein Library. Please contact the Rubenstein Library for further information on accessing this resource.
    Transcript of a speech delivered by Harding to the student volunteers participating in the Mississippi Freedom Summer Project, 1964. Harding discussed: history of the African American experience in America; sexual tension that some volunteers would face in Mississippi; potential black racism in the project; the need for volunteers to try to help build local leadership during the summer.
    - Audiocassette copy (Box 6, Audio-cassette RL10056-CS-0066)
    - Transcript (Box 1)
    - Use copy audiocassette (Box 3, Audio-cassette RL10056-CS-0015)
  - Holland, Ida Mae interviewed by Joseph Sinsheimer, 1987 March 14; 17
    - Original audiocassette, 1 of 2 (Box 6, Audio-cassette RL10056-CS-0067)
    - Original audiocassette, 2 of 2 (Edwin King material duplicates content on RL10056-CS-0072) (Box 6, Audio-cassette RL10056-CS-0068)
    - Use copy audiocassette, 1 of 2 (Box 3, Audio-cassette RL10056-CS-0016)
    - Use copy audiocassette, 2 of 2 (Box 3, Audio-cassette RL10056-CS-0017)
  - Jackson, Jesse - speech, 1985 June 27; 18
    Transcript of a speech delivered by Jackson at the 21st Anniversary memorial service for James Chaney, Andrew Goodman, and Michael Schwerner at the Goodway Baptist Church in Philadelphia, MS.
    - Original audiocassette (Box 6, Audio-cassette RL10056-CS-0069)
    - Transcript (Box 1)
    - Use copy audiocassette (Box 3, Audio-cassette RL10056-CS-0018)
  - Johnson, Rev. Aaron, interviewed by Joseph Sinsheimer, undated; 20
    Former pastor at the First Christian Church in Greenwood, MS. Interview with Sinsheimer. Johnson discussed the development of the Greenwood campaign, 1962-1963.
    - Original audiocassette (Box 7, Audio-cassette RL10056-CS-0070)
    - Transcript (Box 1)
    - Use copy audiocassette (Box 4, Audio-cassette RL10056-CS-0019)
  - Johnson, June interviewed by Joseph Sinsheimer, 1987 May 5; 19
    Leading civil rights activist in Greenwood, MS, during the 1960s. Interview with Sinsheimer. Johnson discussed: her recruitment to the movement by Robert Moses; her beating at the Winona, MS, bus stop; family's reaction to her civil rights activity; Stokley Carmichael's leadership style; the role of Father Nathaniel Machesky in the Greenwood movement; Silas McGhee's sit-in attempts in Greenwood; the boycott of Slim Henderson's store after he beat a local black woman; civil rights activity in Greenwood in the late 1960s and early 1970s.
    - Original audiocassette (Lawrence Guyot on side 1) (Box 6, Audio-cassette RL10056-CS-0064)
    - Original audiocassette (Box 6, Audio-cassette RL10056-CS-0071)
    - Transcript (Box 1)
    - Use copy audiocassette (Box 4, Audio-cassette RL10056-CS-0020)
  - Jordan, David interviewed by Joseph Sinsheimer, 1985 June 13; 21
    Son of Greenwood civil rights activist Cleveland Jordan. Interview with Sinsheimer.
    - Transcript (Box 1)
  - King, Edwin interviewed by Joseph Sinsheimer, 1987 February 23; 22
    Aaron Henry's running mate during the 1963 Freedom Vote campaign; heavily involved in the Jackson, MS, civil rights movement for more than twenty years; served as MFDP delegate to the 1964 Democratic National Convention. Interview with Sinsheimer. King discussed: civil rights activity at Tougaloo College, 1961-1962; role of Mrs. Doris Allison in the Jackson movement; John Salter's role in the Jackson movement; development of student leadership at Tougaloo; interaction between SNCC staff and Tougaloo students, 1962-1963.
    - Original audiocassette (Box 7, Audio-cassette RL10056-CS-0072)
    - Transcript (Box 1)
    - Use copy audiocassette (Box 4, Audio-cassette RL10056-CS-0021)
  - Ladner, Dr. Joyce interviewed by Joseph Sinsheimer, 1986 May 23; 23
    Active in the Mississippi civil rights movement through the 1960s, particularly in Hattiesburg. Interview with Sinsheimer. Ladner discussed: her reaction to the Freedom Rides coming to MS in 1961; relationship with Medgar Evers before he was assassinated; her reaction to the murder of Emmitt Till as a child; her analysis of Robert Moses' leadership style; friction between college-educated Northern SNCC staffers and the Mississippi staff members; the issue of sexism in the civil rights movement.
    - Original audiocassette (Box 7, Audio-cassette RL10056-CS-0073)
    - Transcript (Box 1)
    - Use copy audiocassette (Box 4, Audio-cassette RL10056-CS-0022)
  - Lott, Hardy interviewed by Joseph Sinsheimer, 1986 May 6; 24
    Former city attorney for Greenwood, MS; leader of white opposition to the civil rights movement in Mississippi; defense counsel for Bryan de la Beckwith during his first trial for the murder of Medgar Evers. Interview with Sinsheimer. Lott discussed; the role of Mayor Sampson and Police Commissioner Buff Hammond in city politics; the role of Police Chief Curtis Lary in responding to civil rights demonstrations; how white leaders in the Delta responded to various economic boycott efforts; the role of the Mississippi Power and Light Company in recruiting industry to the Delta; negotiations with John Doar at the Civil Rights Division of the U.S. Justice Dept.
    - Original audiocassette (Box 7, Audio-cassette RL10056-CS-0074)
    - Transcript (Box 1)
    - Use copy audiocassette (Box 4, Audio-cassette RL10056-CS-0023)
  - Lowenstein, Allard - speech, 1979; 25
    Transcript of a speech delivered by Lowenstein at Millsaps College in either 1978 or 1979. Lowenstein discussed: his involvement in the civil rights movement; his recollections of the 1963 Freedom Vote campaign; his recollections of the Mississippi civil rights movement in general.
    - Original audiocassette (Box 7, Audio-cassette RL10056-CS-0075)
    - Transcript (Box 1)
    - Use copy audiocassette (Box 4, Audio-cassette RL10056-CS-0024)
  - Lynd, Staughton and Alice, interviewed by Joseph Sinsheimer, 1985 December 30; 26
    Staughton Lynd served as the Director of the Freedom School Program during the 1964 Freedom Summer Project. Interview with Sinsheimer. The Lynds discussed: planning for the Freedom School program; Moses' impact on the summer volunteers in Oxford, Ohio training sessions for the Summer Project; SNCC staff dynamics; successful elements of the Freedom School program; Moses' opposition to the Vietnam War and his ability to connect it with Mississippi; the development of the Assembly of Underrepresented People; the liberal-left split inside the civil rights movement; the issue of movement "burnout".
    - Original audiocassette (Box 7, Audio-cassette RL10056-CS-0076)
    - Transcript (Box 1)
    - Use copy audiocassette (Box 4, Audio-cassette RL10056-CS-0025)
  - Machesky, Nathaniel interviewed by Joseph Sinsheimer, 1985 June 26; 27